Okay today's דף *daf* is בבא מציעא נט *Bava Metzia Nun Tet*
59 and we pick up at the bottom of נח עמוד ב
Nun-Chet Amud Bet. *Nun Chet Amud Bet* a good מועד *Moed* מועדים
לשמחה *Moadim L'Simcha* to everyone and our learning should be in the
prayer for the protection of חיילים *chayalim* and חיילות *chayalot* and a
speedy end to the war safe return to the hostages and of
course a restoration of some type of peace and civility on our
college campuses. All right and speaking about civility we're in the middle
of a discussion about אונאת דברים onaat devarim *Ona'at Devarim* and we
pick up on the bottom of נח עמוד ב *Nun Chet Amud
Bet* תני תנא *Tani Tana* it is one two three four five
seven lines from the bottom. תני תנא קמי דרב נחמן בר יצחק
*Tani Tana Kamei DeRav Nachman bar Yitzchak* כל המלבין פני panay, חבירו
chaveiro ברבים כאילו שופך דמים *Kol Hamalbin Pnei Chavero B'Rabim Ke'ilu Shofech
Damim* anybody famous line that people have heard: Anybody who whitens
the face of his friend embarrasses his friend to that point that
makes him blanch in public it's as if they spilled blood. אמר
ליה amreilei, שפיר קאמרת *Amar Lei Shapir Ka'amart* so רב נחמן בר
יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* said to this תנא *Tana* that's actually
a very good teaching דחזינא ליה דאזיל סומקא ואתי חיורא *DeChazeina Lei
De'Azil Sumka V'Ati Chivra* we see that what happens when a person
blanches is the redness of the face goes out that's מלבין פני
חבירו malbin pnei chaveiro, *Malbin Pnei Chavero* and white is replaced so
you cause the rushing of blood so it's figuratively as if you
have spilled his blood as if you murdered him. Now the original
meaning of the statement let's not forget is of course the sense
that if you embarrass somebody and it's in public and that destroys
their public reputation not only do they feel horrible but they don't
know if they can go out in public again it's going to
affect how everybody sees him there's something deep deep into a person
that can be cutting and destroying but it's also reinforced here by
the symbolic essence of the rushing of blood as if you spilled
his blood. Okay אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי *Amar Lei Abaye LeRav
Dimi* במערבא במאי זהירי *B'Ma'arava B'Mai Zahiri* what are they particularly careful
about over in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* people want to
be very פרום frum, *frum* what do they want to be careful
about and as you can guess from the context the answer's not
going to be חלב ישראל *Chalav Yisrael*. אמר ליה באחוורי אפי *Amar
Lei B'Achvuri Appei* whitening somebody's face דאמר רבי יוחנן הכל יורדים לגיהנום
חוץ משלושה *De'Amar Rabbi Yochanan Hakol Yordim L'Gehinnom Chutz MiShlosha* all go
to גיהנום Gehinnom *Gehinnom* except for three so that sounds like there
are three people we're about to say who don't go to גיהנום
*Gehinnom* and we're actually the point is the opposite. הכל סליקא דעתך
*Hakol Salika Da'atach* does it really literally mean all people will go
to גיהנום *Gehinnom*? אלא אימא הכל יורדים לגיהנום *Ela Eima Hakol Yordim
L'Gehinnom* everybody goes down to גיהנום *Gehinnom* עולים *Olim* and they will
come back up all those that go down excuse me not everybody
goes down all those who go down will come back up חוץ
משלושה *Chutz MiShlosha* which except three people שיורדים ואין עולים *Sheyordim V'Ein
Olim* they'll go to גיהנום *Gehinnom* and they'll never come back up
ואלו הן *V'Eilu Hein* and these are who they are הבא על
אשת איש *HaBa Al Eshet Ish* somebody who has sex with a
married woman it's not just the severity of עריות *arayot* we're not
mentioning שבת *Shabbos* for example or any of the other עריות *arayot*
incest but this is what that does and how that can destroy
the marriage המלבין פני חבירו ברבים *Hamalbin Pnei Chavero B'Rabim* somebody who
whitens his friend's face in public again public embarrassment shame how that
affects the public's perception of him that completely can destroy a person
והמכנה שם לחבירו *V'Hamachane Shem L'Chavero* and somebody who makes a nickname
for his friend Shorty or Stinky or whatever the name is. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מכנה היינו מלבין *Machane Hainu Malbin* that's
the same as shaming a person because the name probably suggests something
or even if it's not suggesting some particular action if it diminishes
a person it's not the way a person wants to be called
it changes that person's perception in society so that's a very way
why do you have to say that once you've said מלבין *Malbin*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אף על גב דדש ביה בשמיה
*Af Al Gav DeDash Bei Bishmei* even if that already is the
name that is common and people use it anybody who continues using
it is עובר *over* on this because that just reinforces its way
in which this person is perceived and shaped and named and so
on. Now of course that's pretty harsh I mean it's one thing
for the person who comes up with a name to never come
back from גיהנום *Gehinnom* but to say even once it's everybody is
using it I mean there are people who are מקפיד *makpid* never
to use a nickname maybe a shortened version of a name but
never a nickname exactly for this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the question
let's say the person is even okay with it although sometimes people
say they're okay and they're not really okay but it is pretty
harsh that even once it's common that that actually would be the
what do you call it the consequence. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
because it's common the consequence say go to גיהנום *Gehinnom* and don't
come up your face does not become white so it's not מלבין
פני חבירו *Malbin Pnei Chavero* and but רש"י *Rashi* does say nevertheless
the person who is using it רש"י *Rashi*'s language is מכל מקום
זה להכלימו נתכוון *Mikol Makom Zeh L'Hachlimo Nitkaven* so it's not just
you're using it because everybody is using it you're trying to to
embarrass him, but he's been embarrassed plenty already by people calling him
this name. So at least רש"י limits it to a case
where the person who's using this name is intentionally trying to embarrass
him. The מהרש"א Maharsha goes
further. The מהרש"א Maharsha says like this: ולולי פירושו היה נראה דנקט
מכנה שם דוקא כמוציא שם רע אף אם אין חבר מתבייש. V'lulei
perusho hayah nireh d'nakat mechaneh shem davka ke'motzi shem ra, af im
ein chavero mitbaysh. Okay, he says maybe he thinks that it's not
about the person being embarrassed, but it's about just spreading bad report
about the person, but nevertheless you're furthering certain perceptions that people have
by using the name, and then he acknowledges that רמב"ם Rambam doesn't
even say that it's a bad name, it's just any nickname. So
depending on how you interpret this, you know, it could be something
really good to be מחמיר machmir for from, but also something that
could be, you know, very heavy to say you go down to
גיהנום and don't come up. It's worth before we continue go further
again to repeat the point that when people say, "What are the
things that you're מחמיר machmir about?" You know, the fact that the
question about what you're מחמיר machmir about in ארץ ישראל and it's
about בין אדם לחבירו bein adam l'chavero issues.
That's something really to take to heart. Okay, let's take a look
at now we continue last line of נ"ח עמוד ב'. אמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabba Bar Bar Chana Amar
Rabbi Yochanan: נוח לו לאדם שיבא על ספק אשת איש. Noach lo
l'adam she'yavo al safek eshet ish. We did mention adultery, intercourse with
a married woman, and that that was equal to מלבין פני חברו.
malvin p'nei chaveiro. Now we're going to sort of say it a
little differently. Better for a person that he should have intercourse with
a somebody who's doubtfully married, a doubtfully married woman, ואל ילבין פני
חברו ברבים. v'al yalbin p'nei chaveiro barabbim. That would come before embarrassing
somebody in public. Now what type of what's a ספק אשת איש
safek eshet ish like? Why should you be doing that? This woman
might be married, now maybe there's a question if her husband's alive
or dead or so on. But anyway, that is now saying that
the מלבין פני חברו malvin p'nei chaveiro is worse, but where's the
גמרא Gemara getting even to have these in the same conversation? So
let's take a look. מנא ליה מדדרש רבא. Mena lei mid'darish Rava.
From what רבא Rava explicated. דדרש רבא: Didarish Rava: מאי דכתיב? Mai
d'chtiv? What's meant by the verse ובצלעי שמחו? Uvatzali samachu? In my
side,
and this is going to be read as like צלע, tzeila, the
side of the human of אדם Adam that was made into a
woman. נאספו, N'asfu, they gathered against me. קרעו ולא דמו. Kar'u v'lo
damu.
And they tore me and it was not like... Okay, so
ולא דמו v'lo damu and it would not cease, but we'll see
in a minute it's going to be read as like דם, dam,
you know, there would not be blood. Let's take a look how
the גמרא Gemara. interprets this. This is from תהלים Tehillim so this
is דוד. David. דוד המלך. David HaMelech. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. Amar David lifnei HaKadosh
Baruch Hu. דוד David said to God: רבונו של עולם. Ribono Shel
Olam. גלוי וידוע לפניך שאם היו מקרעים בשרי לא היה דמי שותת
לארץ. Galui v'yadua lefanecha she'im hayu mekarr'im b'sari lo hayah dami shotet
la'aretz.
It's you it's clear to you, you are it's obvious to you
that if people were to tear me, you know, would rip my
flesh like Shylock if you rip me if you if you tear
my flesh will I not bleed? If people were to rip my
flesh I would not bleed because of all the fasting that he
I have done, you know, for the sin around בת שבע Batsheva
and the and the child and all of that. So where are
we? שותת לארץ. shotet la'aretz. ולא עוד אלא אפילו בשעה שעוסקים בנגעים
ואהלות. V'lo od ela afilu b'shaa she'oskim b'negaim v'ohalot.
But even when people, now this are learning נגעים Negaim and אהלות,
Ohalot, which is the most difficult area of הלכה, Halacha, so meaning
even תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim are going to stop their learning and
look at how they, you know, and look at how they shame
me. אומרים לי, Omerim li, and they say to me, דוד הבא
על אשת איש מיתתו במה? David, haba al eshet ish mitato b'meh?
דוד, David, if somebody has sex with a married woman, how what's
the punishment? You know, mocking me for my sin of בת שבע
Batsheva with בת שבע. Batsheva. ואני אומר להם, Va'ani omer lahem, and
nevertheless I say to them: מיתתו בחנק. Mitato b'chenek. It's true, the
punishment is strangulation, execution by the court. But ויש לו חלק לעולם
הבא, v'yesh lo chelek l'olam haba, you have a portion in the
world to come. אבל המלבין את פני חברו ברבים, Aval hamalvin et
p'nei chaveiro barabbim,
somebody who whitens his friend's face in public, אין לו חלק לעולם
הבא, ein lo chelek l'olam haba, does not have a portion in
the world to come, and that is of course what you are
doing. You are trying to destroy me and shame me, and nevertheless
no matter what you do to me,
I will you know I'm not going to give you know give
you that satisfaction, and I will be satisfied by the idea that
however terrible my sin is, you know, your sin is worse because
you don't have a חלק
לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. So that's how they read that פסוק
pasuk ובצלעי, Uvatzali, my side, meaning relating to my wife, to בת
שבע Batsheva and so on, and that goes back to the earlier
גמרא Gemara about ספק אשת איש safek eshet ish because based on
whether אוריה Uriah would have died in the war and the assumption
that he gave a conditional גט get to בת שבע Batsheva before
leaving to the war is based on another גמרא. Gemara So if
דוד David could have arranged for you know for him to have
died in the war then retroactively בת שבע Batsheva never would have
been married. So that's the ספק אשת איש. safek eshet ish. Although
his response didn't even deal with a ספק אשת איש, safek eshet
ish, it dealt with you know even a real case of adultery
is not as bad as
מלבין פני חברו. malvin p'nei chaveiro. the white and he’s saying my
blood is already all out of me, so there’s some interesting parallel
going on there and is he embarrassed or not embarrassed? He is
embarrassed but he has a retort to them, so a little bit
not clear. The other thing that’s also worth noting is the נגעים
ואהלות Negaim veOhalot making it like תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim maybe saying
again the point you think you’re so פרום, frum you’re big תלמידי
חכמים Talmidei Chachamim but and oh look you’re going to be פרום
you’re going to defend the faith by talking about how bad this
sin is and embarrassing somebody, actually that is the most terrible sin.
The מהרש״א Maharsha also points out
that נגעים Negaim because it could be because צרעת Tzaraat comes from
לשון הרע Lashon Hara so that could be why that’s being associated.
Okay, now we continue. מר זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב ואמרי לה
אמר רב חנא בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא ואמרי לה אמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחי Mar Zutra bar Tuvya amar
Rav ve'amrei lah amar Rav Chana bar Bizna amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida
ve'amrei lah amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
so somebody here says the following: נוח לו לאדם שיפיל עצמו לכבשן
האש Noach lo leadam sheyapil atzmo lekhivshan ha'esh again this is a
statement that probably many have already heard, better that a person should
allow themselves to be thrown actually literally throw themselves but allow let's
say allow themselves to be thrown into a fiery furnace ואל ילבין
פני חבירו ברבים ve'al yalbin pnei chaveiro barabbim so even if you're
not trying to embarrass somebody
intentionally you should be willing to suffer greatly personally rather than to
even unintentionally bring about shame and embarrassment of somebody else. This is
how terrible public embarrassment is again being compared to loss of life.
Okay and how do we know this? מנלן מתמר Minalan miTamar from
Tamar דכתיב היא מוצאת והיא שלחה אל חמיה לאמר dechtiv hi mutzet
vehi shalcha el chamia leimor she was being taken out and she
sent to her father-in-law saying do you know who to whom these
belong? So you see rather than publicly shaming him she was prepared
to allow herself to be thrown into the fire
rather than publicly shaming him and only gave him the opportunity to
own up himself. Of course פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is
that if she had directly confronted him he would have denied it.
By giving him that space and allowing him to own up that’s
what actually made him actually take responsibility, so it’s not like it
was actually necessary for her to do that to achieve the end
result, but anyway this is how the גמרא Gemara is reading it.
The מהרש״א Maharsha also says that it could be a play on
words היא מוצאת hi mutzet מוצאת mutzet is like להצית lehatzit to
light a fire like it's as if the fire was already being
lit on her she was right in the face of the fire
and nevertheless she would not say it directly. Okay אמר רבי חנינא
בריה דרב אידי Amar Rabbi Chanina brei deRav Idi מאי דכתיב mai
dechtiv what’s meant by the first ולא תונו איש את עמיתו velo
tonu ish et amito do not oppress one person his friend which
we now are saying about אונאת דברים onaat devarim the way your
words can injure somebody which led to מלבין פני חבירו ברבים malbin
pnei chaveiro barabbim which is a variation of that. Anyway what is
meant by this? את עמיתו et amito
why does it say עמיתו amito and not חבירו for example? עם
שאתך בתורה ובמצות אל תונהו im sheitcha beTorah uvemitzvot al tonehu only
somebody who's with you in תורה ומצות Torah uMitzvot do not afflict
them meaning with words, meaning that if somebody is a sinner and
a public sinner not a sinner we all sin דוד המלך David
Hamelech and the point was still אונאת דברים ona’at devarim, but if
somebody is a רשע rasha public sinner and not committed to a
life of תורה ומצות Torah uMitzvot and this was at a time
where that required real like רשעות rishut and breaking away that’s not
our reality right now, that type of a person it’s appropriate to
say derogatory things because you want people to not learn from that
person and to keep their distance. So it only applies to somebody
who is with you in תורה ומצות Torah uMitzvot but not for
issues like relating to monetary cheating and overcharging that would apply to
everyone. אמר רב לעולם יהא אדם זהיר באונאת אשתו Amar Rav leolam
yehe adam zahir beonaat ishto a man should particularly be careful that
his words don’t hurt his wife, cause pain to his wife
and here again you have אונאה onaah even if it’s unintentional presumably
be very careful not to say anything that even might might cause
pain to your wife שמתוך שדמעתה מצויה אונאתה קרובה shemitoch shedimaata metzuya
onaatah krova because her tears are close to the surface her אונאה
onaah is also very near which means classic trope about women being
sensitive and emotional but also just means okay maybe you can say
this to your guy friends and they don't care but you should
be
careful with your
wife she might be particularly sensitive and
bracketing the gendered aspect of this that the גמרא Gemara is saying
it’s still very good מוסר mussar and right and that would make
her the likelihood that words would lead to אונאה onaah would be
much greater could be much greater in those cases. אמר רבי אלעזר
Amar Rabbi Elazar now the idea of crying and what the crying
as a result of the אונאה onaah will do we’ll see in
a minute. אמר רבי אלעזר מיום שחרב בית המקדש ננעלו שערי תפלה
Amar Rabbi Elazar miyom shenechrav Beit Hamikdash nin'alu sha'arei tefilla from the
days that the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash was destroyed the gates of
prayer. You know, if the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is the doorway
to heaven and זה שער השמים, zeh sha'ar hashamayim, if it's destroyed,
so like that access to heaven through our prayers that you know
we pray towards the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's a lot harder
to get through, the doors are locked, שנאמר גם כי אזעק ואשוע
סתם תפילתי, shenemar gam ki ezak va'ashave'a satam tefillati,
even when I cry out and and beseech, my prayers are shut
up, are closed up. ואף על פי ששערי תפילה ננעלו, ve'af al
pi shesha'arei tefillah ninalu, even though the gates of prayer are closed,
שערי דמעות לא ננעלו, sha'arei demaot lo ninalu, the gates for for
tears in are not closed. שנאמר שמעה תפלתי ה' ושועתי האזינה, shenemar
sham'ah tefillati Hashem veshavati ha'azinah, hear God my prayer and listen to
my give ear to my to my beseeching, אל דמעתי אל תחרש,
el dim'ati al techerash,
do not silence yourself, deafen yourself rather from my tears. And Rashi
is sort of reading rather than it's a request don't deafen yourself
from my tears, you will not make yourself deaf, you will certainly
hear my tears. So now if tears are an expression of אונאה
Ona'ah and the gates of tears are not locked, then that means
that the punishment that will come, that God will hear and the
suffering and be responsive to it is much greater, and that's what
we are going to see.
Okay. ואמר רב, ve'amar Rav, Rav says, ואמר רב כל ההולך בעצת
אשתו נופל בגיהנום. ve'amar Rav kol haholech be'atzat ishto nofel beGehennom. Since
we're talking about being careful with a man being careful about his
wife's being sensitive and being hurt by his words, so now we're
going to say something not so nice about wives. Anybody who
follows his wife's advice, בעצת אשתו, be'atzat ishto,
I lost my place, נופל בגיהנום, nofel beGehennom,
will in the end go to Gehennom, meaning it's going to lead
you astray, שנאמר רק לא היה כאחאב, shenemar rak lo hayah keAchav,
don't be like Achav, you know, and it speaks about that he
followed the advice of his wife Jezebel. Now hopefully maybe what Rav
means is even though we're saying about being sensitive and responsive to
your wife, not to the point that if she gives you like
Lady Macbeth or like Jezebel or whatever, you know, gives you advice
actually will be bad, you know, clearly lead you astray. But anyway
let's see, it does sound like it's a more global statement. Let's
see what the Gemara does with this. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי,
amar leih Rav Pappa leAbaye, Rav Pappa to Abaye, והאמרי אינשי איתתך
גוצא גחין ותלחוש לה, ve'ha'amri inshi ittech gutza gachin veselechosh lah, that
don't but don't people say that if your wife is is literally
a midget, is short, then you should bend down and like whisper
to her and have her whisper in your ear, meaning meaning you
know accommodate yourself to your wife and it's so important to be
in relationship, but also not only be in relationship, the idea of
whispering means like to take counsel with her. And you know sometimes
sadly people are dismissive of short people or of, you know, or
other people based on physical attributes and here it's saying like no,
your wife's counsel is so important, you should always you know be
in conversation with her. And there are Gemaras that talk about Rabbi
Eleazar ben Azariah asking, you know, great rabbis asking the wisdom of
their wife in terms of practical situations. So let's see how the
Gemara answers. לא קשיא הא במילי דעלמא והא במילי דביתא. lo kashya
ha bemeili de'alma ve'ha bemeili deveisa. No no no, there's a difference
between things of this world and things of the house. In domestic
matters she knows her household, listen to her whenever it comes to
anything having to do with the home. In broader worldly affairs, you
know, that you could leave you know that's something that here Rav
is saying it's not a good idea to listen to your wife.
You know, that's the old joke right? Guy says like you know
I
you know I handle all the big decisions in the house, what
to do with you know you know how we should be dealing
with the economy and with the you know and with war in
the Middle East and with what's going on in Ukraine and whatever
and I deal with all those, as my wife she deals with
the smaller decisions: where the kids are going to go to school,
how are we you know where how we're going to
you know where we're going to live, you know whether we should
you know whether we should go on vacation, so she deals with
the small decisions I deal with the big ones. So that's you
know what the Gemara here is saying: okay, you the man deal
with the world with the world issues, she'll deal with the domestic
ones, although I don't think the Gemara was saying it in that
way. That's answer number one. Answer number two is לישנא אחרינא הא
במילי דשמיא והא במילי
דעלמא. lishna acharina ha bemeili deshmaya ve'ha bemeili de'alma. No no no,
your wife has very good practical wisdom not only about domestic issues
but even about you know worldly affairs, you know, you can trust
your wife and you should listen to your wife in terms of
practical wisdom. When it comes to religious matters, that's the man's you
know area, that's the man's field.
So that at least fits in, gives a woman a lot bigger
sphere and of course we know socially women were kept out of
like the world of Torah and so on. So so you know
maybe that tones down a bit that that original statement. Okay, moving
on. אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, כל השערים ננעלו חוץ משערי
אונאה. kol hashe'arim ninalu chutz misha'arei ona'ah.
Back to the locked gates, all the gates were locked except for
the gates of אונאה Ona'ah and my tie-in to the combination of
the אונאה Ona'ah and the tears okay before we. or, שנאמר she'neemar
as the פסוק pasuk says, הנה ה' נצב על חומת אנך ובידו
אנך. hineh Hashem nitzav al chomat anach uveyado anach.
God was standing over a wall of, this is translated usually a
plumb line and he was holding onto a plumb line, but here
the word אנך anach means אונאה. onaah. So God is right there
standing and therefore accessible, you can see, it's on top of the
wall, it's not behind the wall and accessible. אמר רב אלעזר, Amar
Rav Elazar, הכל נפרע בידי שליח חוץ מאונאה. hakol nifra bidei shaliach
chutz meonaah. God will pay back, you know, people will get their
punishment from heaven through an intermediary except from אונאה, onaah, God personally
is going to come to the defense of those who are oppressed
by words, חוץ מאונאה, chutz meonaah, שנאמר, she'neemar, ובידו אנך. uveyado anach.
God is holding onto the אנך, anach, אונאה. onaah. אמר רבי אבהו,
Amar Rabbi Abbahu, ג' אין הפרגוד ננעל בפניהם. gimel ein hapargod ninal
bifneihem.
There are three that the divine curtain is not locked in front
of them, maybe a little different image than the gates. אונאה, onaah,
so אונאה onaah as we've said, וגזל vegezel if somebody is, you
know, steals, or is, ועבודה זרה, veavodah zarah, and somebody who worships
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So normally we speak about
עבודה זרה, גילוי עריות, שפיכות דמים, avodah zarah, gilluy arayot, shefichut damim,
the אונאה onaah sort of can fit with the שפיכות דמים, shefichut
damim, and we don't exactly have the גילוי עריות gilluy arayot although
the אונאה onaah was compared to that before. Anyway here we have
אונאה, גזל ועבודה זרה. onaah, gezel veavodah zarah. אונאה דכתיב, onaah dechtiv,
ובידו אנך. uveyado anach. God is going to be there, you know,
holding onto the
אונאה. onaah. גזל דכתיב, gezel dechtiv, חמס ושוד ישמע בה על פני
תמיד, chamas vashod yishama bah al panay tamid, that, you know, that
the violence and plunder will
be heard, it'll be constantly on my face, I God am directly
going to see the evil that's done and take judgment. ועבודה זרה
דכתיב, veavodah zarah dechtiv, העם המכעיסים אותי על פני תמיד, haam hamachisim
oti al panay tamid, in my face they do the עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So these are like direct affronts to God. Now how
do you, you could understand at what this means by a direct
affront to God? עבודה זרה avodah zarah is obvious, right, and the
תורה Torah often says פני, you know, לא יהיה לך אלהים אחרים
על פני. lo yihiyeh lecha elohim acherim al panay. It could be
that the אונאה onaah is because of the צלם אלהים tzelem Elokim
and, you know, seeing somebody as a divine soul and to actually
crush that soul and, you know, that could obviously be seen as
that's the sense of God's face. And גזל gezel is, you know,
the world belongs to God, לה' הארץ ומלואה, leHashem haaretz umloah, we
make a ברכה, bracha, we appreciate that we're given rights to this
world and so on, but ultimately it all comes from God. That's
possibly a way of seeing that these are direct affronts to God.
Okay. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, לעולם יהא אדם זהיר בתבואה.
leolam yehei adam zahir bitvuah.
A person should be very careful about, you know, finances, is essentially
what it means, grain. בתוך ביתו, betoch beito, in his house. שאין
מריבה מצויה בתוך ביתו של אדם אלא על עסקי תבואה. sheein merivah
metzuyah betoch beito shel adam ela al iskei tvuah. That if there's
a lot of contention and fighting in the house, it often has
to do with the fact that finances are tight and that there's
not enough money. שנאמר, she'neemar, השם גבולך שלום חלב חטים ישביעך. hasam
gevulech shalom chelev chitim yasbiech.
He makes your borders with peace, the fat of grain God will
sate you with them. So your borders will be peaceful if you
have food in the home and if you're able to meet your
expenses. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu deamri
inshi, that's what people say. כמשלם שערי מכדא, kemishlam seari mikada,
when the barley is emptied out of the jug, נקיש ואתי תיגרא,
nakish vaati tigra,
then contention comes knocking at the door. Okay, so that was a
common statement, same idea. בביתא, beveita, in the house, knocking at the
house. ואמר רבי חיננא בר פפא, veamar Rabbi Chinana bar Papa, לעולם
יהא אדם זהיר בתבואה בתוך ביתו, leolam yehei adam zahir bitvuah betoch
beito,
you should always be careful about, you know, your expenditures in the
home and that there should always be food available. שלא נקראו ישראל
דלים אלא על עסקי תבואה. shelo nikreu Yisrael dalim ela al iskei
tvuah.
That we were never called poor except when it came to insufficient
grain and food. How do you know that? שנאמר, she'neemar, והיה אם
זרע ישראל ודל. vehayah im zara Yisrael vadal.
And, you know, if the seed of Israel, and רש"י quotes I
think the end of the פסוק, pasuk, it says וידל ישראל, vayeidal
Yisrael, וכתיב, vechtiv, ויחנו עליהם, vayachanu aleihem, וכתיב, vechtiv, וידל ישראל מאד,
vayeidal Yisrael meod,
and that they were very poor, so that was relating to the
lack of grain. Okay. ממדין, mimadyan, from Midian. אמר רבי חלבו, Amar
Rabbi Chelbo, לעולם יהא אדם זהיר בכבוד אשתו. leolam yehei adam zahir
bichvod ishto.
So now we're back to, after that one really disturbing negative statement
about not listening to your wife's advice, now the גמרא Gemara corrected,
you know, very much bracketed that in significant ways and now we're
back to these positive statements. Don't be sensitive to words that could
hurt your wife, it's again always speaking to the man, and actually
be very careful to give your wife honor. wife's respect and dignity.
יהא אדם זהיר בכבוד אשתו שאין ברכה מצויה בתוך ביתו של אדם
אלא בשביל אשתו *Yehe adam zahir b'kvod ishto she-ein bracha metzuya betoch
beito shel adam ela bishvil ishto*, because the blessing that a person
has in their house, it is all because of a man has
is all because of the wife. שנאמר ולאברם הטיב בעבורה *Shene'emar u-le'Avram
heitiv ba'avura*. To Abraham it was good on her sake. And you
know the מהרש"א *Maharsha* reads it, it's like the הטיב *heitiv* is
being read midrashically as God was good to Abraham for Sarah's sake,
not the פשט pshat *pshat* about the מצרים *Mitzrayim* because they wanted
to—פרעה *Paroh* wanted to marry her and so on. Okay. והיינו *V'hainu*,
so it is your wife that brings blessing in the house. והיינו
דאמר להו רבא לבני מחוזא *V'hainu d'amar lehu Rava livnei Mechuza*, that's
what רבא *Rava* said to the בני מחוזא *b'nei Mechuza*, the city
that רבא *Rava* lived in. Okay. אוקירו לנשייכו כי היכי דתתעתרו *Okiru
l'neshaichu ki heichi d'tisatru*, you should show honor to your wives that
you should become wealthy, you should become rich. So there you go
again all the very positive things about the relationship about one's wife.
תנן התם *Tnan hatam*. Okay, so now we're going to get to
that long midrashic statement about אונאה onaah *ona'ah*, המלבין פני חברו *hamalbin
pnei chaveiro* with some
digressions—very interesting about again husband and wife. And now we're going to
get to an extremely famous גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that is being cited
because of the end of the story has to deal with אונאה
ona'ah. *ona'ah*. Let's take a look. תנן התם *Tnan hatam*, we taught
over there. חתכו חוליות ונתן חול בין חוליה לחוליה *chatcho chulyot v'natan
chol bein chulya l'chulya*. Let's say you had an oven and they
would make an oven, a kiln like out of pottery, it would
be essentially like a big pot and they'd put a huge pot
standing on the ground and they'd put a fire in it and
then they'd suspend pots from the mouth. Anyway, so you had this
תנור *tannur*, this oven, and it was made, how it was made
was broken into parts and sand was put between the various parts.
So is that considered still to be a vessel that can become
טמא tamei *tamei*? Because when you break a pottery vessel, it no
longer can become טמא tamei. *tamei*. And maybe it's still considered to
some degree broken because you didn't plaster them together, you have this
sand separating the pieces, or is it now considered once again to
be a vessel and can become טמא *tamei*? Okay, so רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer מטהר *Rabbi Eliezer m'taher*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
said it would be טהור tahor *tahor*, וחכמים מטמאים *v'chachamim m'tam'im*, and
the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* say it would still become טמא *tamei*. And
if it has the ability to become טמא *tamei*. Top of נט
עמוד ב *nun-tet amud bet*. וזהו תנור של עכנאי Tanur shel Achnai
*v'zehu tannur shel Achnei*. This is the תנור *tannur* of עכנאי *Achnei*.
עכנאי *Achnei* means—might be, תוספות *Tosafot* says it might be the name
of a place, but the גמרא *Gemara* interprets the word midrashically. מאי
mai, עכנאי *Mai Achnei*? What does עכנאי *Achnei* mean? אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל שהקיפו דברים כעכנא זו *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel shehikifu
devarim k'achna zu*, that the rabbis, you know, surrounded him, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, with words, they attacked him, argued against him
כעכנא זו *k'achna zu*,
like a snake, you know, like especially also that image of the
snake swallowing its tail, circled around him, וטימאוהו *v'tim'uhu*, and declared it
to be טמא *tamei*. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, *Tanu rabanan*, we taught
in a ברייתא *Baraisa*. באותו היום השיב רבי אליעזר כל תשובות שבעולם
ולא קיבלו הימנו *B'oto hayom heishiv Rabbi Eliezer kol teshuvot sheba'olam v'lo
kiblu heimenu*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* that day gave all responses to
all of the challenges and the rabbis still refused to accept his
ruling. אמר להם *Amar lahem*, so he was like frustrated, like I
gave logical arguments and you still rejected it. So now he had
to appeal to a higher source. He said: אם הלכה halacha כמותי
חרוב זה יוכיח *Im halacha k'moti charuv zeh yochiach*. If the הלכה
halacha *halacha* is like me, let this חרוב *charuv* tree prove that
I'm right. נעקר חרוב ממקומו *Ne'ekar charuv mimkomo*, and it uprooted from
its place מאה אמה *me'ah amah*, 100 אמה *amah* into the heaven—אמרי
ליה ארבע מאה אמה *amri leh arba me'ah amah*, some say 400
אמה *amah*. אמרו Amru, לו אין מביאין ראיה מן החרוב *Amru lo
ein mevi'in re'aya min hacharuv*. That's not a proof. You know, you
did a nice mini-miracle, but that doesn't make a logical argument about
why we should listen to you. If you can't convince us with
your logical argument, then that doesn't prove anything in the area of
הלכה halacha *halacha*. חזר ואמר להם Chazar ve-amar lahem *Chazar v'amar lahem*,
then he said to them: אם הלכה halacha כמותי אמת המים יוכיחו
*Im halacha k'moti amat hamayim yochi'chu*. If the הלכה halacha *halacha* is
like me, let this
stream of water prove that I'm right. חזרו אמת המים לאחוריהם *Chazru
amat hamayim l'achoreihem*, so they went—so the water that was flowing one
way started flowing backwards the other way. אמרו Amru, לו אין מביאין
ראיה מאמת המים *Amru lo ein mevi'in re'aya me'amat hamayim*. You do
not bring it from a stream of water. Again, that's irrelevant in
the type of arguments in the בית מדרש beis medrash *beit midrash*.
מהרש"א *Maharsha* says, you know, that maybe part of it is that
when people don't accept your arguments, you know, you think that they're
not listening and you think that they're being, you know, obstinate or
whatever, and they just are not agreeing with you. So he was
basically—the metaphor of the
wine was—excuse me, of the water was that water—you know, the גמרא
*Gemara* compares תורה Torah *Torah* to water because water always finds the
low ground, and that you have to be humble. So that the
מהרש"א *Maharsha* says he was trying to indicate to them that it's
your arrogance that is not allowing you to, you know, to accept
and listen to my arguments.
מהרש"א *Maharsha* has a symbolism by the חרוב *charuv* tree, which is
a little less direct. Okay. חזר ואמר ve'amar להם אם הלכה halacha
כמותי כותלי בית המדרש Beis HaMedrash יוכיחו.
If the הלכה halacha is like me let the walls of the
בית המדרש prove it. הטו כותלי בית המדרש ליפול Hatu koslei beis
hamedrash lipol they started you know getting ready to fall
so they started collapsing. גער בהם רבי יהושע. Ga'ar bahem Rabbi Yehoshua.
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua yelled at them. אמר להם אם תלמידי חכמים
מנצחים זה את זה בהלכה אתם מה טיבכם. Amar lahem im talmidei
chachamim menatzechim zeh es zeh bahalacha atem mah tivchem.
If Torah students are you know beating out one another it's a
question: is it collaboration or competition, right? This type of energy in
a בית מדרש beis medrash is often very competitive in the sense
of well or like who's going to win who's going to you
know have the stronger argument and beat out and win and so
on.
So and that's maybe significant for this story that it's being seen
of in such of this harsh and you know competitive but that's
what he's saying if תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim if one group is
beating out another group in הלכה halacha what is that your issue
you walls? Why is that something that's relevant to you?
לא נפלו מכבודו של רבי יהושע Lo naflu mikvodo shel Rabbi Yehoshua
they did not fall because of the respect of רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua ולא זקפו מפני כבודו של רבי אליעזר velo zakfu mipnei kvodo
shel Rabbi Eliezer but they didn't stand back
up because of the respect of רבי אליעזר ועדיין מטים ועומדים ve'adayin
matim ve'omdim and they're still inclined and leaning. So again you know
it's interesting to think that רבי אליעזר is trying to basically feel
like you're these are you know like what you're doing is maybe
saying what you're doing is against nature you're resisting obvious you know
my obvious arguments so show things that are that will be against
you know somehow against nature you're trying to destroy maybe he said
the what goes on in the בית מדרש beis medrash and your
resistance to hearing my arguments is destructive so the walls of the
בית מדרש should be destroyed and they said it's not destructive we
just don't agree with you so you know it's really two people
that can't hear one another and therefore the appeal to these outside
powers. Okay.
חזר ואמר להם then he said to them אם הלכה כמותי מן
השמים יוכיחו. im halacha kemosi min hashamayim yokhichu. Let it let it
be proved from heaven you know maybe when they were saying you
can't bring proof from this you know I've been interpreting to say
it's not part of how הלכה halacha. is done you don't there's
no proof to your argument by the fact that you did these
miraculous things but maybe he understood them to say that you know
who knows how to interpret it it's it's the it's not explicit
what those signs mean. So he says fine let a heavenly voice
come out and make it very clear and explicit. יצתה
בת קול Yatzta bas kol a heavenly voice came out ואמרה מה
לכם אצל רבי אליעזר ve-amra mah lachem etzel Rabbi Eliezer why are
you you know what's your place to be arguing with רבי אליעזר
שהלכה כמותו בכל מקום she-halacha kemoso bechol makom that we all the
הלכה halacha is always like him so he's right. עמד רבי יהושע
על רגליו Amad Rabbi Yehoshua al raglav רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua stood
up on his feet ואמר לא בשמים היא ve-amar lo bashamayim hi
and it's not in the heavens okay even when if it's explicit
and it's coming out of the heavens that's not how הלכה halacha
is done. God you stay out of it הלכה halacha is given
to us to interpret to apply to take a vote and in
the end we go by the majority and you know even if
there's some even if maybe somebody has a better argument you can't
convince everybody else in the end this is the way הלכה is
decided. So this of course is a classic classic you know audacious
גמרא לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi that about the power of
human beings in תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh that it's their
interpretation and their application and even if it's not consistent with what
God intended or what it says up in שמים shamayim if they're
trying to find it with integrity and this is the conclusion that
they reach that is what defines הלכה not a heavenly voice not
what's up in
שמים. shamayim. מאי לא בשמים היא? Mai lo bashamayim hi? What so
now the גמרא explicates what that means אמר רבי ירמיה שכבר ניתנה
תורה מהר סיני amar Rabbi Yirmiyah she-kvar nitna Torah me-Har Sinai אין
אנו משגיחין בבת קול. ein anu mashgichin bevas kol. The תורה Torah
was already given at הר סיני Har Sinai God you gave you
did your part you gave us the תורה שבכתב Torah she-bichtav now
a divine voice you know is not relevant in deciding הלכה. You
know there could be נבואה nevuah and a נביא navi can tell
you to temporarily override a מצוה mitzvah but in terms of deciding
what the הלכה is you know as as that is a system
that was given over to us. וכבר
כתבת בהר סיני בתורה U-kvar katavta be-Har Sinai ba-Torah and it's already
written in the תורה Torah, אחרי רבים להטות acharei rabbim le-hattos that
you go by the majority.
Okay so that is the normally when people learn this סוגיא sugya
they stop there. Great story לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi God
keep out of it. אבל בוא נראה Aval bo nireh but let's
see. The גמרא is not done.
אשכחיה רבי נתן לאליהו. Ashkechei Rabbi Natan le-Eliyahu. רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
found אליהו Eliyahu bumped into אליהו הנביא. Eliyahu Hanavi. אמר ליה מאי
עביד קודשא בריך הוא בההיא שעתא Amar lei mai avid Kudsha Brich
Hu be-hahi sha'ata how was God responding at that moment like did
He feel like you
know I can't believe it, I wanted them to פסקן pasken like
Rabbi Eliezer and they wouldn't listen to me? אמרו, so they, so
אמר ליה, קחייך, kachayich, he was laughing, ואמר נצחוני בני נצחוני בני.
nitzchuni banai nitzchuni banai. My children have been victorious over me.
So they bested me, they got the better of me, they're right.
So that's nice little insertion and you can tell it's an insertion
in the story because it's a shift to Aramaic, is there to
just reassure us
that if we had any doubt that this is exact God is
behind this as well. God wants ultimately it to be decided by
humans even with the בת קול bas kol having come out. Now,
by the way, the word of נצחוני nitzchuni is very much echoes
תלמידי חכמים מנצחים זה את זה בהלכה. talmidei chachamim menatzchim zeh es
zeh b'halacha. Who's going to win, who's going to be victorious? And
that's sort of, so now they were so strong, they were not
only victorious over Rabbi Eliezer, they were victorious over me. But at
least God took it in good humor, but obviously Rabbi Eliezer did
not. Rabbi Eliezer could not allow his sense of what's right and
wrong to give in just based on these procedural laws. So let's
see what happens.
אמרו, they said, אותו היום הביאו כל טהרות שטיהר רבי אליעזר ושרפום.
oto hayom hevi'u kol teharos shetiher Rabbi Eliezer vesarfum. That day they
brought all the food that Rabbi Eliezer said had come in contact
with this oven, Rabbi Eliezer said that and the oven had come
in contact with something that was טמא or whatever, in the airspace,
and Rabbi Eliezer said it's all okay, it's all טהור tahor because
the oven never became טמא. So they took all of those things
that he said were טהור ושרפום באש vesarfum ba'eish and they burnt
them in a fire. And it didn't just say they went and
they פסקן pasken to people and made them correct. It didn't seem
like they were just trying to correct the הלכה that was אסור,
assur, it actually they made a, it sounds like they really made
a public and this gets to מלבין פני חבירו, like a very
strong public statement. They, the rabbis, gathered it all together and burned
it, so there should be no question who the הלכה is like.
ונמנו עליו וברכוהו, venimnu alav uverchuhu, and they voted and they actually
put him in a type of a נידוי, niduy, a type of
a form of חרם cherem of
excommunication because it sort of evokes this whole question about
זקן ממרא zakein mamrei also for the authority of the בית דין
beis din and of the court, you need that to be people
that accept the procedures and how law is determined. So they felt
that that was really necessary to defend their authority to make these
types of harsh types of ways of wrapping up this case, of
making it clear who was right and where the authority lies.
Okay, so where were we? ואמרו מי ילך ויודיע, ve'amru mi yeilech
veyodia, who would go and tell Rabbi Eliezer that he was put
in that we put him in חרם? cherem? אמר להם רבי עקיבא,
amar lahem Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva said, because he has to know,
because he has to practice appropriately and he's going to wonder why
people aren't going to
be having anything to deal with him and getting within his ארבע
אמות, arba amos, within four cubits. There's the very poignant story that
goes together with this of Rabbi Eliezer on his deathbed, that the
חכמים couldn't sort of come within his ארבע אמות arba amos because
he had been in חרם cherem and he presumably never did the
type of תשובה teshuva or submission that would have been required for
them to have removed the חרם. cherem. He was a very very
strong, rigid type of a character, as we can see from the
story. אמר להם רבי עקיבא אני אלך, amar lahem Rabbi Akiva ani
eilech, I will go, שמא ילך אדם שאינו הגון ויודיעו, shema yeilech
adam she'eino hagun veyodi'u, unless an inappropriate person go and inform him
and maybe won't understand how to let him know because we'll see
Rabbi Akiva's going to inform him in a very sensitive way, or
maybe just because
he'll feel degraded because of this person that's coming and informing him,
disrespected, ונמצא מחריב את כל העולם כולו, venimtza machriv es kol ha'olam
kulo,
and that will lead to Rabbi Eliezer destroying the world like he
has these
powers. We already saw he uprooted a carob tree and whatnot. מה
עשה רבי עקיבא, mah asah Rabbi Akiva, what did Rabbi Akiva do?
לבש שחורים ונתעטף שחורים, lavash shechorim venisa'ateif shechorim, he dressed himself in
black, wrapped himself in a black טלית, tallis, וישב לפניו בריחוק ארבע
אמות, veyashav lefanav berichuk arba amos,
and stood four אמות amos away from Rabbi Eliezer in an obvious
way that he wouldn't enter into the ארבע אמות. arba amos. So
he himself made himself in mourning to show how grieved he was
by this what was done. It was necessary what was done, but
how painful and how grieved he was. אמר לו רבי אליעזר, amar
lo Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer said to him, עקיבא, Akiva, עקיבא מה
יום מיומיים, Akiva mah yom miyomayim, why are you what's today different
than you're dressed in black and you're staying far away from me?
אמר לו רבי, amar lo rebbi, he said, Rebbe, my teacher, because
Rabbi Eliezer was one of the teachers of Rabbi Akiva. כמדומה לי
שחברים בדילים ממך. kemidumeh li shechaverim bdilim mimcha. I have the impression
that your colleagues are keeping away from you. So he sort of
alluded to him that he was in חרם cherem but without saying,
oh, you're in חרם. cherem. Which again, a student saying to the
Rebbe, the words of saying somebody saying to you you're in חרם
cherem are very painful words, so he just suggested it to him.
אף הוא קרע בבגדיו וחלץ מנעליו, af hu kara bevagadav vechalatz minalav,
so then Rabbi Eliezer acted as somebody is supposed to act on.
He did קריעה keriah and he took off his shoes and ונשמט
וישב על גבי קרקע venishmat veyashav al gabi karka and he sat
by on the ground and וזלגו עיניו דמעות vazalgu einav dmaot and
tears flowed from his eyes, remember the tears from before. לקה העולם
שליש בזיתים ושליש בחיטים ושליש בשעורים, Laku haolam shalish bazeitim veshalish bechitim
veshalish biseorim,
and that caused there to be terrible, his pain and his suffering
and his crying, remember the gates of אונאה ona'ah. of crying are
not sealed, that caused there to be terrible disastrous consequences in the
world, that a third of the olives and of the a third
of the grain and a third of the of the barley all
were destroyed in some type of a freak plague or weather or
who knows what. ויש אומרים אף בצק שבידי אישה טפח, Veyesh omrim
af batzek shebeyadei ishah tapach,
even dough in a woman's hands
would spoil, so again clearly these miraculous powers of Rabbi Eliezer. תנא:
אך גדול היה באותו היום, Tana: Ach gadol hayah baoto hayom, שבכל
מקום שנתן בו עיניו רבי אליעזר נשרף, shebechol makom she-natan bo einav
Rabbi Eliezer nisraf, or אף גדול af gadol is a different version,
great anger there was on that day that in every place where
Rabbi Eliezer would look at, it would be burned. Was he intentionally
burning it or just his pain was causing bringing about this destruction?
Not clear. ורבן גמליאל היה בא בספינה, Verabban Gamliel hayah ba besfinah,
and even Rabban Gamliel because apparently as we'll see he was the
נשיא, nasi, so any
a very harsh act like this had to be done under his
auspices. So when he, Rabbi Eliezer, was informed about what was decided,
he happened to be on a boat. עמד עליו נחשול לטבעו, Amad
alav nachshol letavo, a wave was, you know, looked like it was
going to drown and upturn the boat. אמר: כמדומה לי שאין זה
אלא בשביל רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס, Amar: Kimdumeh li she-ein zeh ela
bishvil Rabbi Eliezer ben Hyrkanos, it seems to me that this could
be no other reason than Rabbi Eliezer ben Hyrkanos and the terrible
destruction this is wreaking in the world that such a person like
him was put into חרם. cherem. עמד על רגליו ואמר: ריבונו של
עולם, גלוי וידוע לפניך שלא לכבודי עשיתי ולא לכבוד בית אבא עשיתי,
Amad al raglav ve-amar: Ribono shel Olam, galui veyadua lefanecha she-lo lichvodi
asiti velo lichvod beit abba asiti, he stood up and he said,
Master of the World, it is well known to you that
what I did I did not do for my honor
and didn't do it for the honor of my father's house, it
wasn't anything personal and it wasn't about כבוד, kavod, אלא לכבודך שלא
ירבו מחלוקת בישראל, ela lichvodecha she-lo yirbu machloket be-Yisrael,
but for Your honor
that there should not be
increased debate, disagreement in Israel.
Obviously מחלוקת machloket could be a good thing but ultimately it leads
to finding the truth, but there has to in the end of
the day be a halachic authority that decides. And if everybody's constantly
undermining it, ultimately it's like the זקן ממרא zaken mamre of the
תורה, Torah that is going to could be very destructive. Now not
necessarily, we live in a time of
halachic pluralism, sometimes there's some places where they say in this rabbi's
town they followed his practices even though they were minority practices. So
it doesn't, but somehow the clash here, there was a concern it
really could have undermined the authority of the בית דין, Beit Din,
and it was the time when there was more centralized authority and
therefore he felt that this was necessary. Okay, so let's see what
happens. אלא שלא ירבו מחלוקת בישראל נח הים מזעפו, Ela she-lo yirbu
machloket be-Yisrael, nach hayam mizaapo,
so the ocean settled down from its anger, from its, you know,
from the terrible storm. אימא שלום דביתהו דרבי אליעזר, Ima Shalom deviteihu
de-Rabbi Eliezer, now Ima Shalom was the wife of Rabbi Eliezer. There's
stories about Ima Shalom.
And
אחותיה דרבן גמליאל, achoteih de-Rabban Gamliel,
and she was the sister of Rabban Gamliel. So Rabban Gamliel and
Rabbi Eliezer were brother-in-laws through Ima Shalom. הויא, Havya, she was. מההוא
מעשה ואילך, Me-hahu maaseh va-eilach, from that day onward, לא הוה שבקה
ליה לרבי אליעזר למיפל על אפיה, lo havah shavkah lei le-Rabbi Eliezer
le-mipal al appeih, she never allowed her husband Rabbi Eliezer to do
תחנון, Tachnun, to do נפילת אפים, nefilat appayim, because he would somehow
there was a concern that at that moment he would let out
his suffering and his pain and his sense of being afflicted and
hurt and that would have horrific consequences as we have seen.
Because you know תחנון Tachnun starts with ויאמר דוד אל גד צר
לי מאד נפלה נא ביד ה׳, Vayomer David el Gad tzar li
meod niplah na beyad Hashem, like I am very afflicted, and it
talks about crying and all of that.
ההוא יומא ריש ירחא הוה, Hahu yoma reish yarcha havah, on a
particular day was ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, ואיחלף לה בין מלא לחסר,
Ve-itchalaf lah bein malei le-chaser, she got confused whether it was the
previous month was twenty-nine day month or thirty day month. So she
thought it was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and he didn't have to
you don't do תחנון Tachnun on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, she didn't
have to be on guard, but it actually turned out that it
wasn't ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. איכא דאמרי אתא עניא וקאי אבבא, Ika
de-amri ata anya ve-kaei ababa, or some say actually when a poor
person came to the door and needed some צדקה. tzedakah. אפיקה ליה
ריפתא, Apikah lei rifta, by the time she managed to hand him
a loaf of bread, אשכחתיה דנפל על אנפיה, ashchateih de-nafal al anpei,
so he had managed to do נפילת אפים. nefilat appayim. This also
gets to the question about listening to the advice of your wife,
it wasn't how did she get him to not do it? She
must have told him why she didn't want him to do it,
or she came up with something to distract him, but then... Why
wouldn't she always do it later? So if she already told him
not to do it, is he listening to the advice of his
wife? Not listening? It seems like he's not listening if she's not
there to oversee, he's going to do תחנון. Tachanun. So what happened?
אמר לה קום, Amra leh kum, so she said to her husband
to Rabbi Eliezer, "Get up! קטלתיה לאחי, Kataltia l’achi, you have killed
my brother. I am sure that you in your תחנון Tachanun poured
out your heart to God, and that I am sure will lead
to, you know, my brother being punished because of the way, the
suffering he brought to you." קום לחי. Kum lachi. אדהכי נפק שיפורי
מבי
רבן גמליאל, Ad'hachi nafak shipurei mibei Rabban Gamliel,
and then not soon afterwards, the announcement came, the shofar was blown
from the house of Rabban Gamliel, דשכיב, d'shachiv, that he had died.
אמר לה, Amar lah, so Rabbi Eliezer said, מנא ידעת, Mina yadat,
"How do you know that?" אמר לה, Amra leh, "How did you
know that would happen?" She said to him, "כך מקובלני מבית אבי
אבא, Kach mekublani mibei avi abba, this is the tradition I have
going back, you know, to my father, my grandfather's house, a handed
down tradition: כל השערים ננעלים חוץ משערי אונאה, Kol hashe'arim nin'alu chutz
misharei ona'ah, all of the gates are locked except for the gate
of אונאה." ona'ah, So this famous story of Rabbi Eliezer and the
תנור של עכנאי was all to tell us the power of אונאה.
Now what's interesting here is, you know, it's not exactly אונאת דברים,
it's not words, I mean it was actions, which okay, it's still
same idea, it's devastating to a person, but they burnt his טהרות,
taharot, you know, and what do... I mean there were words, they
put him in נידוי niduy and in חרם, cherem, but the Rabbis
do put people in חרם, cherem, you know, and presumably it was
justified, or was it justified, was it not, or you know, it
seems like it is, I mean the Torah's concerned about זקן ממרא,
zaken mamre, about people that could undermine the authority, but maybe there
was a sense that somehow another path could have been found, it
didn't have to be so מנצחים, menatzchim, you know, it didn't have
to be so much like, you know, like horns locking, maybe some
other more path could have been found to resolve it in a
different way. Maybe what it's also telling us is that sometimes, you
know, there is a decision that has to be made and it's
the right decision, but that does not mean erase the fact about
the people that are hurt in the process and their hurt and
pain is very real as well. So, and there's just no getting
around that and sometimes that's, you know,
on the one hand it's the cost of the of the of
this difficult hard decision, but also in this in this story, it's
the cost that had to be paid not just by Rabbi Eliezer
but by Rabban Gamliel and everybody else as well because they brought
it about. So really it's a really important story not just for
the לא בשמים היא, lo bashamayim hi, but to be reflective about
the end of the story and its and that significance and the
whole point of the אונאה, even when it might have been necessary.
Okay, now we end. תנו רבנן, our Rabbis taught: המאנה את הגר
עובר בשלושה לאווין, Hama’aneh et hager over bishlosha lavin, one who afflicts
the גר, ger, a convert, transgresses three negative prohibitions,
והלוחצו עובר בשניים, Vehahochatzo over bishnayim, and somebody who, you know,
לוחץ lochaitz with here, like means to afflict, but in this context
it means like monetarily cheats a גר, ger, also transgresses
three... two, excuse me, two. מאי שנא מאנה, Mai shna ma’aneh, why,
how is it different in the case of verbally afflict,
דכתיבי שלושה לאווי: dechtivi shlosha lavim: גר לא תונה ger lo toneh
and וכי יגור אתך גר בארצכם לא תונו אתו, vechi yagur itcha
ger be'artzechem lo tonu oto, that's two, and ולא תונו איש את
עמיתו, velo tonu ish et amito, the one we've been dealing with,
general prohibition about words of affliction, וגר בכלל עמיתו, veger bichlal amito,
and a גר ger is included in your neighbor. So that's why
you get three by גר. ger. לוחצו נמי שלושה כתיבי, Lochatzo nami
shlosha ktivi, by לוחצו lochatzo it also says three. Where does it
say it?
כתיבי ולא תלחצנו, ktivi: velo tilchatzenu, וגר לא תלחץ, veger lo tilchatz,
ולא תהיה לו כנושה, velo tihyeh lo k’nosheh, and says do not
be on him like a, you know, like a creditor in terms
of, you know, money being a source of affliction, particularly about cheating,
אונאת ממון. ona’at mamon. Okay,
וגר בכלל הוא, veger bichlal hu, אלא אחד זה ואחד זה בשלושה,
ela echad zeh ve'echad zeh bishlosha, fine, I change it back, or
I change it, you're right, they're both three לאווין. lavin. תניא רבי
אליעזר הגדול אומר, Tanya Rabbi Eliezer hagadol omer, Rabbi Eliezer Hagadol says:
מפני מה הזהירה תורה בל"ו מקומות ואמרי לה במ"ו מקומות בגר, mipnei
mah hizhira Torah b'lamed vav mekomot v'amrei lah b'mem vav mekomot bager,
why did the Torah say in thirty-six places and some forty-six, depends
on how you count them, you know, to be careful with the
not to afflict the גר ger and not to make him suffer
and not to oppress him, why is it so many times it
says it? מפני שסורו רע, mipnei shesoro ra, because his turning is
bad, which is normally understood to mean that he that, you know,
he if you say these words that make him feel marginal, it's
there's a greater chance that he will abandon the faith and go
back to where he came from. So, you know, that's I mean
that might very well be that might be true, it might obviously
it might not be true, and sometimes that's a real problem that
people are constantly suspicious of, you know, converts or not. there could
be that suspicion hovering over. But, you know, there's also the basic
reason that the תורה says is because this is somebody that came
from the outside and is likely to be treated as marginal, and
we know גרים הייתם בארץ מצרים, gerim hayitem b'eretz mitzrayim, and we
know how painful that is and therefore we have a double responsibility
to make
sure
to make sure that that person understands that they're equally one of
us. So, anyway, but he's saying that there's also this consequence. מאי
דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, I mean מאי,
now what's meant וגר לא תונה ולא תלחצנו כי גרים הייתם בארץ
מצרים? v'ger lo toneh v'lo tilchatzennu ki gerim hayitem b'eretz mitzrayim? So
it's exactly that פסוק pasuk which I just explained what the פשט
was. Let's see what the גמרא does with it.
תניא רבי נתן אומר, Tanya Rabbi Natan omer, מום שבך אל תאמר
לחברך. mum she'bach al tomar l'chavercha. A blemish in you, do not
say to your friend. והיינו דאמרי אינשי, v'hainu d'amri inshi, that's what
people say, דזקיף ליה זקיפא בדיקותיה, d'zakif lei zakifa b'dikutei, he who
has had somebody hanged, executed and hanged in their family, like a
skeleton in their closet, לא נימא ליה לחבריה זקיף בינותא, lo neima
lei l'chavrei zakif binassei, should not say to his friend, hey could
you hang a fish for me, because that reflects poorly on him.
Okay, now notice by the way what the point here is. The
point here is you have somebody that was hanged in your family
and you say to your friend, hey would you mind stringing up
these fish for me, then that's going to remind other people about
this hanging that happened in your family and it'll wind up hurting
you. Okay, so as opposed to reading it כי גרים הייתם בארץ
מצרים, ki gerim hayitem b'eretz mitzrayim, you should have particular empathy and
sympathy and understanding and therefore do everything in your power to help
the גר ger and to not make them feel marginal, it's reading
it actually as if you go ahead and say something bad to
the גר ger about the fact that he came from the outside,
ultimately it reflects poorly back on you. And therefore you shouldn't say
it. So maybe sometimes, calling on people for their empathy is less
effective as calling on them in terms of their own self-interest. So
by calling it מום שבך אל תאמר לחברך mum she'bach al tomar
l'chavercha that like people in glass houses shouldn't throw stones and it's
just going to make you look bad, for some people maybe that's
the way to get the message through about why they need to
be careful even though basic human empathy
ideally should be the thing that does it. Okay, we'll stop here.